<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Threads | fizwidget]]></title>
  <link href="http://fizwidget.github.io/blog/categories/threads/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://fizwidget.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-07T23:15:59+09:30</updated>
  <id>http://fizwidget.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Russell]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Implicit Futures in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://fizwidget.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/implicit-futures-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-03T02:20:05+09:30</updated>
    <id>http://fizwidget.github.io/blog/2014/07/03/implicit-futures-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Say we&rsquo;re writing a program that performs several time-consuming operations, like network requests, disk accesses, or complex calculations. We want them to execute concurrently, but we also want our code to remain simple and easy to understand. There are many different ways of approaching this problem, but in this post I&rsquo;ll focus on <em>implicit futures</em> and how they can be implemented in Ruby.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This code demonstrates the type of scenario we&rsquo;re dealing with:</p>

<p>``` ruby
a = foo.expensive_call_1
b = bar.expensive_call_2
c = baz.expensive_call_3</p>

<p>other_stuff</p>

<p>result = a + (b * c)
```</p>

<p>We perform one or more time-consuming operations, potentially do something else, then use the results of the operations.</p>

<p>In the code above, the time-consuming operations are executed sequentially. This results in very poor performance (the CPU might be forced to sit idle while a network request completes for example). Also, the call to <code>other_stuff</code> won&rsquo;t begin running until all three of the previous calls have finished, even though it doesn&rsquo;t depend on their results.</p>

<p>This is the solution we&rsquo;re working towards:</p>

<p>``` ruby
a = future { foo.expensive_call_1 }
b = future { bar.expensive_call_2 }
c = future { baz.expensive_call_3 }</p>

<p>other_stuff</p>

<p>result = a + (b * c)
```</p>

<p>(<em>If you&rsquo;re unfamiliar with Ruby, <code>foo { bar }</code> is equivalent to <code>foo(lambda: bar())</code> in Python</em>)</p>

<p>The expensive calls are now executed asynchronously, and <code>other_stuff</code> can begin running immediately. If line 7 is reached before all three results are available, the main thread will automatically block and wait for them to finish.</p>

<p>Neat! How on Earth do we implement this though&hellip;? At first glance, it looks like we&rsquo;d need to build it into the language itself. As we&rsquo;ll see though, that&rsquo;s not necessary &ndash; languages like Ruby and Python are already flexible enough to support this kind of thing.</p>

<h2>Threads in Ruby</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ll use Ruby&rsquo;s <code>Thread</code> class to do most of the heavy-lifting. Here&rsquo;s a quick primer on it:</p>

<p><code>ruby
t = Thread.new { 2 + 2 }
t.value # =&gt; 4
</code></p>

<p><code>Thread.new</code> spawns a thread to execute the given code block, and <code>t.value</code> returns the thread&rsquo;s result (waiting for it to finish if necessary).</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s rewrite our original code to use <code>Thread</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby
a = Thread.new { foo.expensive_call_1 }
b = Thread.new { bar.expensive_call_2 }
c = Thread.new { baz.expensive_call_3 }</p>

<p>other_stuff</p>

<p>puts a.value + (b.value * c.value)
```</p>

<p>This almost gets us where we want to be, but not quite.</p>

<h2>Explicit vs implicit</h2>

<p>In the code above, we have to explicitly retrieve the results by calling <code>value</code> on the futures. This isn&rsquo;t quite what we&rsquo;re after &ndash; they&rsquo;re <em>explicit</em> futures rather than <em>implicit</em> futures.</p>

<p>This might not seem like much of an issue, but consider what would happen if we wanted to pass a result to another piece of code. We could either:</p>

<ol>
<li>Call <code>value</code> on the future and directly pass along the result.</li>
<li>Pass along the future itself, and let the other piece of code call <code>value</code> when it needs the result.</li>
</ol>


<p>Neither of these options are very good. Option 1 can result in suboptimal performance, because we&rsquo;re calling <code>value</code> before we really need to (remember that <code>value</code> might block execution if the result isn&rsquo;t ready yet).</p>

<p>Option 2 is isn&rsquo;t very good either, because it limits the reusability of the other piece of code (which would now only be able to work with futures).</p>

<p>Implicit futures don&rsquo;t have either of these issues. The code that uses them can remain blissfully ignorant of what they are, and no blocking will occur until the result is actually used (i.e. a method is called on it).</p>

<h2>Delegating method calls</h2>

<p>To summarise what we&rsquo;re trying to achieve, we want the future object to appear as though it were the result object. When we call a method on it, it should delegate the call to the result (blocking if necessary until the result becomes available).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not immediately obvious how we can delegate methods like this. The future should be able to work with all types of result objects, so we don&rsquo;t know in advance which methods need forwarding.</p>

<p>Ruby has a rather interesting feature called <code>method_missing</code> that comes in handy here. Calling a non-existent method normally results in an error, but if we define a method called <code>method_missing</code>, Ruby will call that instead.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a quick demo:</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Useless
  def method_missing(method_name, *args, &amp;block)</p>

<pre><code>puts "Someone called '#{method_name}' on me."
puts "I was given arguments: #{args}"
puts "Now let's call the block I was given:"
block.call
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>well = Useless.new
well.this_is_weird!(&ldquo;yup&rdquo;) { puts &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t even&hellip;&rdquo; }
```</p>

<p>This gives the following output:</p>

<p><code>plain
Someone called 'well_this_is_weird!' on me.
I was given arguments: ["yup"]
Now let's call the block I was given:
I don't even...
</code></p>

<p>So, our future can use <code>method_missing</code> to intercept method calls. We still need to actually forward the intercepted method though &ndash; this is where <code>send</code> comes in. It&rsquo;s defined on all Ruby objects, and lets us dynamically call any method:</p>

<p><code>ruby
some_object.send(method_name, args, &amp;block)
</code></p>

<p>To summarise, our future can intercept method calls with <code>method_missing</code> and forward them to the result using <code>send</code>.</p>

<h2>Putting it all together</h2>

<p>We now have everything we need to implement an implicit future. We can:</p>

<ol>
<li>Use <code>Thread</code> to:

<ul>
<li>Asynchronously compute the result.</li>
<li>Block execution if the result is requested before it&rsquo;s ready.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Use <code>method_missing</code> and <code>send</code> to delegate method calls to the result.</li>
</ol>


<p>The code actually ends up being very simple:</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Future
  def initialize(&amp;block)</p>

<pre><code>@thread = Thread.new { block.call }
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def method_missing(name, *args, &amp;block)</p>

<pre><code>@thread.value.send(name, *args, &amp;block)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>When a future is created, a thread is immediately spawned to execute the given code block. When a method is called on the future, it simply forwards it to <code>@thread.value</code> (which will block if the thread hasn&rsquo;t finished running yet).</p>

<p>To make it slightly easier to use, we&rsquo;ll define a standalone <code>future</code> function that creates and returns a <code>Future</code> object:</p>

<p><code>ruby
def future(&amp;block)
  Future.new(&amp;block)
end
</code></p>

<p>We can now create future objects like this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
f = future { expensive_call }
</code></p>

<p>This looks exactly like what we set out to achieve. Brilliant! Might be a good idea to check if it works though&hellip;</p>

<h2>Testing time</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a sanity-check:</p>

<p>``` ruby
f = future do
  puts &ldquo;Future: Started.&rdquo;
  sleep(4)
  puts &ldquo;Future: Finished.&rdquo;
  &ldquo;yeeeeaaaaaaaahh&rdquo;
end</p>

<p>sleep(2)</p>

<p>puts &ldquo;Attempting to use the result.&rdquo;
puts f.upcase
```</p>

<p>To mimic an expensive operation, I&rsquo;ve placed a call to <code>sleep</code> in the code given to the future. The call to <code>f.upcase</code> should cause the main thread to block for several seconds until the result is ready. Here&rsquo;s the output we get:</p>

<p><code>plain
Future: Started.
Attempting to use the result.
Future: Finished.
YEEEEAAAAAAAAHH
</code></p>

<p>It worked!</p>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s try more realistic example. We&rsquo;ll download a bunch of webpages and record how long it takes, with and without futures:</p>

<p>``` ruby
require &lsquo;benchmark&rsquo;
require &lsquo;open-uri&rsquo;</p>

<p>urls = [
  &ldquo;<a href="https://www.google.com">https://www.google.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com">https://www.microsoft.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="http://www.abc.net.au">http://www.abc.net.au</a>&rdquo;,
  &ldquo;<a href="http://www.reddit.com">http://www.reddit.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://www.atlassian.com">https://www.atlassian.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://duckduckgo.com">https://duckduckgo.com</a>&rdquo;,
  &ldquo;<a href="https://www.facebook.com">https://www.facebook.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org">https://www.ruby-lang.org</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="http://whirlpool.net.au">http://whirlpool.net.au</a>&rdquo;,
  &ldquo;<a href="https://bitbucket.org">https://bitbucket.org</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://github.com">https://github.com</a>&rdquo;, &ldquo;<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com">https://news.ycombinator.com</a>&rdquo;
]</p>

<p>def download_with_futures(urls)
  pages = urls.map do |url|</p>

<pre><code>future { open(url) { |f| f.read } }
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  # Wait until all downloads have finished by calling a method on each future.
  pages.each { |page| page.length }
  pages
end</p>

<p>def download_without_futures(urls)
  urls.map do |url|</p>

<pre><code>open(url) { |f| f.read }
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>Benchmark.bm do |b|
  b.report { download_with_futures(urls) }
  b.report { download_without_futures(urls) }
end
```</p>

<p>And the results are&hellip;</p>

<p>``` plain</p>

<pre><code>   user     system      total        real
</code></pre>

<p>   0.160000   0.040000   0.200000 (  2.561927)
   0.110000   0.030000   0.140000 ( 13.774315)
```</p>

<p>13.8 seconds down to 2.6 seconds. Neat!</p>

<h2>Caveats</h2>

<p>The <code>Future</code> class given above isn&rsquo;t exactly production-ready. If you were using it in a real project, you&rsquo;d want it to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Capture exceptions that occur during the thread&rsquo;s execution and re-throw them when the result is accessed.</li>
<li>Inherit from <code>BasicObject</code> instead of <code>Object</code>, so the methods defined on <code>Object</code> are also delegated to the result.</li>
<li>Use a thread pool to prevent the system from being overloaded by a large number of threads.</li>
<li>Probably a bunch of other things I haven&rsquo;t thought of.</li>
</ul>


<p>A basic implementation in 8 lines of code isn&rsquo;t too shabby though :P</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Futures are awesome. Ruby is awesome. That is all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
